## MAHESH MUPPASANI

Fullstack Software Engineer

mahesh.muppasani007@gmail.com https://linkedin.com/in/mahesh-muppasani/ https://maheshmuppasani.vercel.app/ +1989491-1302

Software Engineer with 5+ years of experience in fullstack development, requirements gathering and business automation. Recognized for exceptional contributions to customer experience and efficient management of business functions. Proficient in Java, Spring Framework, AWS, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, MySQL, React.js, and Angular.

## **Work Experience**

## Full Stack Engineer (Internship) | BigLynx Inc, Bellevue, WA, US

Jan 2024 - Nov 2024

- Developed a scalable CRM platform using Java with microservices using Spring Cloud, PostgreSQL and GraphQL for efficient data management and fault tolerance, ensuring scalability and 99.9% uptime consistently.
- Integrated Dynamics 365 CRM with Node.js and Power BI for real-time dashboards and streamlined customer management, automating business reporting by 50% and cutting manual effort by 40%.
- Performed consistent maintanance, implemented redis caching, query optimization and developed stored procedures in PostgreSQL, optimizing system performance which resulted in an improved latency of 65%.

# IT Support Engineer (Part-time) | Central Michigan University, Mt.Pleasant, MI, US Jan 2023 - Dec 2023

- Leveraged AWS lambda and AWS CloudWatch Logs to improve ETL processes for the university's website, enhancing scalability and performance, resulting in an improved latency of 60% to handle over 10,000 concurrent users.
- Integrated Tableau UI into administrator dashboard for real-time visualization of student and semester enrollment trends, improving data accessibility, enabling data-driven decisions, and cutting reporting time by 30%.

#### Software Engineer (Full-time) | Innova Solutions, Hyderabad, India

Aug 2021 - Dec 2022

- Leveraged Java with Spring Cloud and Spring MVC to develop a scalable Inventory Monitoring System, enhancing data-driven decision-making, server-side performance, and reducing data inconsistencies by 100%, while improving system response time by 30%.
- Utilized AWS S3, and AWS Lambda to deploy a cloud-based solution for Inventory Management, ensuring high availability and fault tolerance. Integrated AWS CloudWatch for monitoring and optimized system scalability, leading to a 40% reduction in infrastructure costs.
- Built a robust administrator portal leveraging Apollo GraphQL APIs integrated with React.js, automating 100% of order processes and order fulfillment, promoting efficient data retrieval while cutting order processing time by 80%.

#### Associate Software Engineer (Full-time) | Innova Solutions, Hyderabad, India

Dec 2019 - Aug 2021

- Developed an e-commerce platform for a leading pharmaceutical company, automating order processing, driving a 50% sales increase and boosting user experience by 70% leveraging Angular with GraphQL APIs.
- Rebuilt an inventory tracking app migrating from ASP.NET server pages to modern React with TypeScript, maintaining zero downtime, improving system performance by 75% and reduced latency by 60%.

## **Projects**

## BigLynx CRM Portal | Java, Spring Framework, PostgreSQL, Redis, React.js

Jan 2024 - Nov 2024

- Built a robust CRM portal using Java (Spring Boot) with microservices architecture, leveraging Spring Cloud and GraphQL APIs for efficient data retrieval and Integrated Grafana for performance optimization, enhancing customer data management and improving system efficiency by 30%.
- Designed and integrated Power BI dashboards to provide real-time insights on sales performance and customer trends, accelerating decision making and streamled reporting by 45%.
- Optimized backend performance by effective coding standards, code refactoring, and implementing caching strategies using Redis, resulting in a 65% improvement in response times and system reliability.

## MH Fulfilment | Java, AWS, Spring Cloud, Spring MVC, MongoDB, React with TS Aug 2021 - Dec 2022

- Leveraged AWS Lambda with Java, Spring MVC and React.js with TypeScript to develop a scalable administrator site and efficient Inventory Management System, enabling seamless processing of 8,000+ customer orders per month.
- Streamlined order lifecycle processes leveraging microservice architecture with Spring Cloud and GraphQL schemas, resulting a 39% increase in average order volume through cross-team collaboration.

#### Nutrascriptives Direct | Node.js, JWT, Angular, Semantic UI, Figma

Dec 2019 - Aug 2021

- Developed an innovative e-commerce app using Node.js, Angular, GraphQL APIs and Figma, automating the order lifecycle, achieving 60% of automation while ensuring 100% order accuracy consistently.
- Contributed to an increase in sales revenue with an exceptional growth rate of 41%, significantly enhancing the user interface and experience with responsive design principles and Semantic UI.

## **Volunteer Experience**

### Front End Panel Recruiter | Innova Solutions

Aug 2021 - Dec 2022

• Played a pivotal role in the recruitment process at Innova Solutions by taking over 100+ technical interviews as a front-end panel member, helping the firm to filter and onboard the applicants, resulting in 30% hiring efficiency.

## Technical Mentor - Web Development Training Program | Innova Solutions

Aug 2021 - Feb 2022

• Mentored a team of 5 trainees at Innova Solutions, teaching key front-end technologies such as JavaScript, React.js, Angular, and other frameworks. The team delivered three projects, boosting customer revenue by 29%.

### **Core Skills**

C++, Java, Python, JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML, CSS, Spring Framework, AWS, Node.js, React.js, Angular, Vue.js, NgRx, Redux.js, RxJS, Tailwind CSS, Bootstrap, Material-UI, Semantic UI, Webpack, Vite, Babel, REST API, GraphQL, Apollo Client, Apollo Server, Axios, Fetch API, Socket.IO, Express.js, MySQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, MSSQL, OAuth, Bcrypt, Auth0, Firebase Authentication, Jest, Git, GitLab, Responsive web design, Developer Tools, UI/UX, Figma, Agile software development Lifecycle, SCRUM, Waterfall, data structures, object-oriented design, Algorithm design, Computer Science essentials, Problem Solving

#### **Education**

Master of Science in Information Systems | GPA: 3.9/4.0

lan 2023 - Dec 2024

Central Michigan University, MI, USA

Bachelor of Electronics and Communication Engineering | GPA: 3.6/4.0

Jul 2016 - May 2020

K L University, Andhra Pradesh, India

#### **Awards**

#### Best Intern of the Year | BigLynx Inc

Aug 2024

Won "Best Intern of the Year" award at BigLynx Inc. for outstanding contributions to the BigLynx CRM Portal, boosting client efficiency by 30% and improving system performance and decision-making.

#### Customer Champion Award | Innova Solutions

Oct 2021

Received the Customer Champion Award in recognition of exceptional contributions by guiding the team in completing 8 weeks of tickets in just 4 weeks and fostering customer satisfaction.